Holsoe County Surveys, 1981-1994
Indiana University Digital Library Program
Holsoe County Surveys,
1981-1994
Liberian Collections Indiana University 504 North Fess Avenue Bloomington, IN 47408 Phone: (812) 856-0782 Email: liberia@indiana.edu http://www.onliberia.org
Holsoe, Svend E.
LCP1997/001
4 cubic feet; 4 records cartons
This collection consists of census materials for various counties in Liberia including correspondence, maps, reports, statistics and indexes. Many of the different Chiefdoms and Clans are represented.
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Over the course of his prolific scholarly career, anthropologist Svend Einar Holsoe has greatly advanced our knowledge and understanding of the history and culture of the peoples of Liberia. During his youth, Holsoe’s family lived in Liberia for nine years. His interest in a close study of this country and its peoples began during his senior year in high school. Asked to write an essay on his hometown for his senior English course, Holsoe chose Monrovia, only to discover the dearth of material on the nation and its people. It was at this moment, he says, that he dedicated himself to finding and collecting printed materials on Liberia.
Unparalleled in his dedication to the preservation of documents and artifacts on Liberia, in 1997 Holsoe donated his collection of materials to Indiana University’s Archives of Traditional Music, Liberian Collections Project, Mathers Museum, and Art Museum. A product of his years of research and relentless materials collection, The Svend E. Holsoe Collection is one of the largest and most comprehensive deposits of resources on the West African nation. The Collection includes: copies of Liberian Government Archive Documents between 1824-1983; extensive genealogical records, including analyses and family trees developed from these records; political, institutional, social and cultural surveys from the 1980s Liberia Rural Radio Project; field notes and oral history tapes of Vai and Bandi research; Vai script materials, including research notes, examples and articles; and slides and photos spanning decades and covering many geographical areas and activities. Due to looting and the destruction of Liberia’s National Archives during the civil war that began in 1989, the Liberian Government Archives, part of the Holsoe Collection, contains the only extant copies of important historical and cultural documents.
During his career, Holsoe published numerous important scholarly contributions on Liberia. As early as 1966, Holsoe's article, “The Condo Confederation in Western Liberia,” was published in the Liberian Historical Review. Over the next thirty years, Holsoe wrote twenty-seven articles related to Liberia for numerous publications. Holsoe and D. Elwood Dunn collaborated on the first edition of The Historical Dictionary of Liberia ( 1984 ). He followed up this major project as a co-author of A Land and Life Remembered: Americo-Liberian Folk Architecture ( 1988 ). More recently, he co-edited African American Exploration in West Africa ( 2003 ).
A co-founder of the Liberian Studies Association, Holsoe created and edited the Liberian Studies Journal from 1968 to 1978, as well as a Liberian Studies Monograph Series. In 1999, Indiana University awarded Holsoe the Chancellors’ Medallion in honor of his unique contributions to scholarship. In presenting the honor, Chancellor Kenneth Gros Louis said of Holsoe: “We know, thanks to his collecting and preserving, thanks to his selfless donation to a public university which will make his work available to all in what we hope will be perpetuity, that Svend Holsoe has done more than his part to ensure that much of what constitutes the country and the cultures of Liberia will remain, and that we, as stewards of his materials, will harvest richly from his efforts.” Indeed, Holsoe's scholarly legacy and invaluable collection will long remain an indispensable source of information and inspiration to future scholars of Liberia.
Scope and Content
7 published handbooks, plus correspondence, maps, rough drafts, fieldnotes. Some government publications, esp. prior census materials (1920s-1970s) in supplementary material. Lofa, Bong, Grand Gedeh, Nimba (rural counties) are best represented. Maryland, Sinoe, and Grand Kru counties are not yet represented.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index this collection.
Names
Holsoe, Svend E.
Places
Liberia -- History -- 20th Century
Liberia -- Politics and Government -- 20th Century
Bomi County (Liberia)
Bong County (Liberia)
Grand Bassa County (Liberia)
Grand Cape Mount County (Liberia)
Grand Jide County (Liberia)
Lofa County (Liberia)
Margibi County (Liberia)
Montserrado County (Liberia)
Nimba County (Liberia)
River Cess County (Liberia)
Topics
Indigenous Peoples -- Liberia
Processing Note
Arranged October 2003. Some large maps and computer disks removed. Countries are arranged alphabetically, but Holsoe's original order roughly correlating to geography is maintained within each. Each country has a separate report not yet processed.
Administrative Information
- BOMI COUNTY (Container 1)
  - General Folders (Box 1)
    - Maps
    - Rough Notes #1
      - Exceprts from Bai T. Moore "On the Dewoin People", n.d.
      - Names List (bibliography?), n.d.
      - Central Government Officials, 7 Nov 1983
    - Rough Notes #2
      - History, 17 Oct 1991
      - Bomi Territory Administrators, 1974
  - Bopolu-Suehn District Folders (Box 1)
    - Dei Cheifdom
      - Bulugba Clan
      - Deigbo Clan
      - Gbaavon Clan
      - Zo Clan
    - Lofa-Gola Chiefdom
      - Boje Clan
      - Gbor Clan
      - Gobla Clan
      - Kpo Clan
      - Mana Clan
      - Senje Clan
      - Teh Clan
  - Mecca District Folder: (Box 1)
    - Mecca Chiefdom
      - Uppa Mecca
      - Lower Mecca
    - St. Paul District Notes
- BONG COUNTY (Box 1)
  - General Folders (Box 1)
    - Maps
      - Commerical topographical map, 1968
      - County map showing districts, 1986
      - Photocopies of topographical map
    - Notes 1#
      - Paramount Chiefs, 1915-1960s
      - Excerpt from Daily Log, 3 Feb 1984-5 Feb 1984
    - Notes #2
      - Language Maps of Liberia and Gbanga Station, n.d.
      - Population Statistics from Census, 1978
      - Maps of Kpelle Chiefdoms, 1978-1979
      - Distances between Gbanga and Palela, 12 Jan 1986
      - Structural Diagrams of County Government, 3 Jul 1983
      - Photography of Published Photo: "The Paramount Chief at Gbanga with his Favorite Son", n.d.
      - Table: "Distribution of Localities by Major Languages", n.d.
      - Handbook Draft: "IV. Current Institutional Activities", 21 Dec 1983, 12 Jan 1984
      - Distances Between Gbanga Various, n.d.
    - Notes #3: "Kpelle Central Province"
      - Superintendents, 1964-1983
      - District Divisions, 1932
      - Sections for Against Government, 1917
      - Schools in Zone 6
      - Names propositions from Daily Observer Bong Crier, 1982-1983
      - Census Photocopies, 1974
      - Handbook Draft: "IV. Current Institutional Activities", 2 June 1983
      - "People's Magisterial Court" other notes on Couty System, n.d.
      - "Number of Health Workers by Professional Categories", 27 June 1983
      - Rubber Corporation, n.d.
      - County Officials, 27 June 1983
      - Wells, n.d.
    - Notes #4
      - Fieldnotes, n.d.
      - Trip Report, 27 Feb 1984
      - Handbook Work Plan, Aug 1982-June 1983
      - Notes on Handbook Design, 1984
    - Bibliography, 1984
  - Jorkwele District Folders (Box 1)
    - Jorkwele Chiefdom, 1984
      - Maps Photocopies
      - Census
      - Handbook excerpt: "Historical Information
    - Jorkwele Chiefdom/Behekwele Clan, 1983
      - Maps photocopies
      - Survey responses
    - Jorkwele Chiefdom/Gbanshe Clan, 1983
      - Maps photocopies
      - Survey responses
    - Jorkwele Chiefdom/Jorkpolu Clan, 1984
      - Maps photocopies
      - Survey responses
    - Jorkwele Chiefdom/Behekwele Clan, 1984
      - Maps photocopies
      - Survey responses
    - Jorkwele Chiefdom/Sheansu Clan, 1983
      - Maps photocopies
      - Survey responses
  - Kokoya District Folders (Box 1)
    - Kokoya Chiefdom
    - Kokoya Chiefdom/Bonwein Clan
    - Kokoya Chiefdom/Kokoya Clan
    - Kokoya Chiefdom/Senwein
    - Kokoya Chiefdom/Tukpabli
  - Panta-Kpai District Folders (Box 1)
    - General
    - Panta Chiefdom
    - Panta Chiefdom/Panta Clan
    - Panta Chiefdom/Wuna Clan
    - Kpai Chiefdom
    - Kpai Chiefdom/Wetua Clan
    - Kpai Chiefdom/Wolata Clan
  - Salala District Folders (Box 1)
    - Nyaforkwele Chiefdom
    - Nyaforkwele Chiefdom/Kornorye Clan
    - Nyaforkwele Chiefdom/Kuwrongwoala Clan
    - Nyaforkwele Chiefdom/Kpatoli Clan
    - Nyaforkwele Chiefdom/Nyaforkwele Clan
  - Suakoko District Folders (Box 1)
    - Suakoko Chiefdom
    - Suakoko Chiefdom/Gaiye Clan
    - Suakoko Chiefdom/Kpatawee Clan
    - Suakoko Chiefdom/Kporyorkwele Clan
    - Suakoko Chiefdom/Suakoko Clan
    - Suakoko Chiefdom/Tongboyah Clan
    - Suakoko Chiefdom/Yandewein Clan
    - Suakoko Chiefdom/Zeansu Clan
- GRAND BASSA COUNTY (Box 1)
  - General Folders (Box 1)
    - Maps
    - Rough Notes #1, Exceprts from Liberian News (Sept 1924); Bill's Notes "Concerning New Cess" (n.d.); 1962 County Census Publication (1962)
    - Rough Notes #2
      - Draft, 5 Nov 1991
  - District #1 Folders (Box 1)
    - Rough Notes
    - 1A Cheifdom (Joya), Doe-Doe Wein Clan; Soniwein Clan; Wehnsohn Clan
    - 1B Chiefdom (Tenor), Nyonwein Clan; Mehwein Clan; Sewein Clan
  - District #2 Folders (Box 1)
    - Notes
    - 2A Cheifdom (Glarkon), Goingbe Clan; Hoegban Clan; Kabli Clan; Marbli Clan; Marloe Clan; Peter Harris Clan; Varmbo Clan
    - 2B Cheifdom (Camwood), Boe-Glayn Clan; Chan #1 Clan; Chan #2 Clan; Gbor Clan' Gogowein Clan
  - District #3 (Gbezohn) Folders (Box 1)
    - Notes
    - 3A Cheifdom (Gbezohn), Dorzohn-Goryah Clan; Gorbli Clan; Neekreen Clan; Zeewein Clan
    - 3B Chiefdom (Gbewen), Gbarwein Clan; Gbaryah Clan; Seeyah Clan; When-Gba-Kon Clan; Wrogba Clan
    - Municipality of Buchanan
  - District #4 (Timbo) Folders (Box 1)
    - Notes
    - 4 Chiefdom, Doe Gbahn Clan; Gianda Clan; Grand Kola Clan; Neepu Clan; New Cess Clan; Trade Town Clan
    - Gbeta Kru Chiefdom
- GRAND CAPE MOUNT COUNTY (Box 2)
  - General Folders (Box 2)
    - Maps:, Tourist map travel guide (1965); Commercial topographical map (1968); Photocopies of topographical maps (n.d.)
    - Notes #1, Acts passed by legislature (1932)
    - Report Draft, 7 Nov 1991
    - Locality Index, 7 Nov 1991
  - District Folders (Box 2)
    - Report Draft: Gawula-Kone District, 7 Nov 1991
      - Gawula Chiefdom/Kiadil Clan
      - Gawula Chiefdom/Kiahon Clan
      - Gawula Chiefdom/Kiazolo Clan
      - Gawula Chiefdom/Manobala Clan
      - Gawula Chiefdom/Zorgbor Clan
      - Tombe Chiefdom/Fusaa Clan
      - Tombe Chiefdom/Kiakpongbor Clan
      - Tombe Chiefdom/Kiatamba Clan
      - Tombe Chiefdom/Seiwana Clan
      - Tombe Chiefdom/Sombai Clan
      - Tombe Chiefdom/Sombai Badalo Clan
      - Gola-Kone Chiefdom/Dablo Clan
      - Gola-Kone Chiefdom/La Clan
      - Gola-Kone Chiefdom/Mana Clan
      - Gola-Kone Chiefdom/Gion Clan
      - Gola-Kone Chiefdom/Kiazolo Clan
      - Gola-Kone Chiefdom/Zolu Duma Clan
    - Report Draft: Tewo District, 7 Nov 1991
      - Kpokpa Chiefdom/Dagole Clan
      - Kpokpa Chiefdom/Dazambo Clan
      - Kpokpa Chiefdom/Kposo Clan
      - Kpokpa Chiefdom/Semavule Clan
      - Kpokpa Chiefdom/Sokpo Clan
      - Kpokpa Chiefdom/Kposo Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Dagoh Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Dasen Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Fahnbulleh Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Getawe Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Golafali Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Jaleiba Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Kiawu Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Kiatamba Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Kroma Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Mendemassa Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Paaseve Clan
      - Tewo Chiefdom/Sambola Clan
- GRAND GEDEH COUNTY (Box 2)
  - General Folders (Box 2)
    - Bibliographies, 1984, undated
    - Rough Notes
    - Sociocultural Report, 1984-1985, undated
  - Gbason District Folders (Box 2)
    - Rough Notes
    - Biai Chiefdom
      - Report Draft, Oct 1985
    - Gbason Chiefdom
      - Report Draft, Oct 1985
    - Gbason Chiefdom, Map tracings
    - Bibliography
  - Tchien Distict Folders (Box 2)
    - Tchien Chiefdom
    - Tchien Chiefdom/Gborgo-Niabo Clan
    - Tchien Cheifdom/Menyon-Kaira Clan
    - Tchien Chiefdom/Menzon-Gboro Clan
  - Konobo District Folders (Box 2)
    - Rough Notes
    - Konobo Chiefdom, Gbilibo-Gbalu Clan; Glio-Twabo Clan
    - Putu Chiefdom, Gbaegbo Clan; Jibehgo Clan
  - Gbepo District Folders (Box 2)
    - Notes and Draft, 19 Dec 1986
    - Maps and Tracings
    - Chedepo Chiefdom
  - Webo District Folders (Box 2)
    - Rough Notes
    - Map Tracings
    - Survey Results, Feb 1984
    - Sabo Cheifdom, Sabo-Palipo Clan; Kitiebo-Glaro Clan
    - Webo Cheifdom, Tuobo Clan; Webo Clan
    - Bound Report, 1986
  - Sahlipia-Ma District
    - Report, 1986
- LOFA COUNTY (Box 2)
  - General Folders (Box 2)
    - Maps
    - Rough Notes #1
      - Roads, Jan 1986
      - Handbook Draft: "Bondi Chiefdom", n.d.
      - County Government Structure, 18 Nov 1985
      - Handbook Draft: "A Socioogical History", 18 May 1985
      - Kwandi-Bomi Towns List, n.d.
      - Topographical Maps of Voinjama District, n.d.
      - Bunde-Wubomai Chiefdom, 1985
      - Map distance scales (photocopy), n.d.
      - Lofa County Profile -- health, literacy, n.d.
    - Notes
      - Hembe, n.d.
      - Holy Cross Mission, n.d.
      - Handbook Draft: "Tengia Clan", n.d.
      - Handbook Draft: Mamdee Dukuly Section", n.d.
    - Notes #3:, Paramount Chiefs in Voinjama District
    - Notes #4
      - Lofa County clan list, 1974
      - "Distribution of Localities by Major Language", 1981
      - Education, 1977
    - Notes #5, Outline of Liberia with major cities; Project Correspondence (23 Feb-23 Apr, 1985); Government Structural Diagram (n.d.)
    - "Incomplete Preliminary Draft", 9 June 1985
    - Bibliography, 28 Dec 1981
  - Bopolu District Folders (Box 2)
    - Rough Notes
    - Bopolu Chiefdom, Bunde-Mandingo Clan; Gonbeya Clan; Tawola-Wonnoa Clan
    - Bokomu Clan, Bokumu Clan; Goua Clan
    - Belle Chiefdom
    - Belle Chiefdom - "Materials for a History of Western Liberia: The Belle", 1971
    - Belle Chiefdom - "The Traditions, History, and Folklore of the Belle Tribe", 1969
    - Belle Chiefdom/Batti Clan
    - Belle Chiefdom/Lobaizu Clan
  - Gbama District Folders (Box 2)
    - Rough Notes
    - Goje Chiefdom, Gbama Clan; Yangaya Clan
    - Kongba Chiefdom, Jawajei Clan; Zui Clan
  - Guma District Folders (Box 2)
    - Guma Chiefdom/Mende Clan
  - Kolahun District Folders (Box 2)
    - Survey Results, Apr 1984
    - Bandi Chiefdom
    - Bandi Chiefdom/Hasala Clan
    - Bandi Chiefdom/Hembe Clan
    - Bandi Chiefdom/Lucasu Clan
    - Bandi Chiefdom/Tahamba Clan
    - Bandi Chiefdom/Wanwuma Clan
    - Bandi Chiefdom/Wulukoha Clan
    - Kissi Chiefdom/Tengia Clan - Reort Draft, 1992
    - Kissi Chiefdom/Tengia Clan - Reort Draft, 1986
    - Kissi Chiefdom/Waum Clan
  - Voinjama District Folders (Box 2)
    - Maps
    - Rough Notes - Handbook Draft: "A Social Institutional Survey", 1993
    - Survey Results, Apr 1984
    - Bunde-Wubomai Cheifdom
    - Bunde-Wubomai Cheifdom/Bunde Clan
    - Bunde-Wubomai Cheifdom/Lower Workor Clan
    - Bunde-Wubomai Cheifdom/Upper Workor Clan
    - Kwandu-Bomi Chiefdom/Kwandu-Bomi Clan
  - Zorzor District Folders (Box 3)
    - Survey Results, Apr 1984
    - Kpelle Chiefdom - Report Draft, 1987
    - Kpelle Chiefdom - Report Draft, May 1986
    - Kpelle Chiefdom/Gbalein Clan
    - Kpelle Chiefdom/Palama Clan
    - Kpelle Chiefdom/Vavala Clan
    - Loma Chiefdom - Report Draft, 1993
    - Loma Chiefdom/Bluyema Clan
    - Loma Chiefdom/Bluyema Clan
    - Loma Chiefdom/Gissima Clan
    - Loma Chiefdom/Ziehma Clan
    - Bound Report: Kolahun District, 1986
    - Bound Report: Voinjama Zorzor Districts, 1986
- MARGIBI COUNTY (Box 3)
  - General Folders (Box 3)
    - Maps
    - Rough Notes, Excerpts from "Missionary Exploration of Liberia" (1871); administration maps (n.d)
  - Mamban-Kaba District Folders (Box 3)
    - Notes on Marshall Territory
    - Kaba Chiefdom
    - Mamban Chiefdom
  - Other Districts: (Box 3)
    - Marshall City
    - Blarkon
    - Tobi
    - Kakata
    - Firestone Plantation
- MONTSERRADO COUNTY (Box 3)
  - General Folder: Rough Notes
  - Monrovia Folder: Monrovia Environs
  - Careysburg District
- NIMBA COUNTY (Box 3)
  - General Folders (Box 3)
    - Commercial Maps, 1968
    - Rough Notes #1, Political Structure; Excerpts from "Uberliefurungen aus Nordestliberia" (Traditions from Northern East Liberia) (1939)
    - Published Maps, "Carte schematique des courants migratoires" (1948); "Die Dan", n.d.; "Mano Gio Clans and Chiefdoms", n.d.; Excerpts from field notebook (distances to Saklipia to Tapita), n.d.
    - Rough Notes #2, Letters and Envelopes to County Commissioners, 3 Feb 1986; Distances in Saklipia, n.d.; Photocopy of St. Jerome's Field Trip Notebook, Apr-May 1984; Photocopy of Lorette's Field Trip Notebook, Apr-May 1984
    - Report Draft Table of Contents, 6 June 1987
    - Bibliography, 6 Mar 1994
  - Saklipia District Folders (Box 3)
    - Saklipia-Ma Chiefdom/Report Draft, 4 May 1986, Gbana Clan; Gbei Clan; Lisonoh Clan; Loo Clan; Wei Clan; Zaan Clan
  - Sanikwelle District Folders (Box 3)
    - Sanikwelle-Ma Chiefdom/Report Draft, 3 May 1986, Bein Clan; Bua Clan; Gaa Clan; Gbehng Clan; Sei Clan; Yaamein Clan
    - Sanikwelle-Ma Chiefdom/Rough Notes
    - Yarpea-Ma Chiefdom/Report Draft, p Mar 1994, Duo Clan; Gbein Clan; Kpaiyee Clan
  - Boo-Kehlei District Folders (Box 3)
    - Boo-Kehlei Chiefdom
    - Boo-Kehlei Chiefdom/Report Draft, 19 June 1990, Boo Clan; Kehlei Clan; Yurpea Clan
  - Kanple District Folders (Box 3)
    - Gbehlei-Geh Chiefdom
    - Gbehlei-Geh Chiefdom/Gbehlei Clan
    - Gbehlei-Geh Chiefdom/Gborple Clan
    - Gbehlei-Geh Chiefdom/Sorlei Clan
    - Gbehlei-Geh Chiefdom/Srohlei Clan
    - Gbehlei-Geh Chiefdom/Zor Clan
  - Kpabli District Folders (Box 3)
    - Kpabli Chiefdom, Dyorworwli Clan; Kpabli Clan
  - Tapita District Folders (Box 3)
    - Amalgamated Gio Chiefdom
    - Amalgamated Gio Chiefdom/Report Draft, 19 June 1990
    - Amalgamated Gio Chiefdom/Doo Clan
    - Amalgamated Gio Chiefdom/Gbea Clan
    - Amalgamated Gio Chiefdom/Gblor Clan
  - Yawein-Mehnsonoh Distric Folders (Box 3)
    - Yawein-Mehnsonoh Chiefdom
    - Yawein-Mehnsonoh Chiefdom/Report Draft, Jan 20 1990, Mesonoh Clan; Yawein Clan; Zehnla Clan
  - Zo-Geh District Folders (Box 3)
    - Zo-Geh Chiefdom
    - Zo-Geh Chiefdom/Butulu Clan
    - Zo-Geh Chiefdom/Gbao Clan
    - Zo-Geh Chiefdom/Yalei Clan
    - Zo-Geh Chiefdom/Zo Clan
  - Gbi-Doru District Folders (Box 3)
    - Gbi-Doru Chiefom, Doru Clan; Gbi Clan
    - Bound Report #1: Saklipia Sanikwelle Districts, 1987
    - Bound Report #2: Saklipia Sanikwelle Districts (copy), 1987
- RIVER CESS COUNTY (Box 3)
  - General Folders (Box 3)
    - Maps
    - Notes
      - Population Census of River Cess Territory 1962
  - River Cess (Timbo) District Folders (Box 3)
    - Notes
      - River Cess District Established (retyped) 1923
    - 5A Chiefdom
    - 5C Chiefdom
    - Gbeta Kru Chiefdom
    - Rock Cess Interior
  - Moweh District Folder: (Box 3)
    - 5B Chiefdom
- SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL (Box 4)
  - Resources on Neighboring West African Nations (Box 4)
  - Conference: "How to Put Liberia Back Together", 10 May 1991, Handouts; Handwritten Notes; "African Demos" vol. 1, n. 4 (Box 4)
  - Survey Notes and Bibliographies (Box 4)
    - List of Wells
    - "Research Survey Coverage Area", 13 Dec 1984
    - Lofa History Bibliography, 30 Nov 1985
    - Ethnography Bibliography, n.d.
    - General Bibliography, n.d.
    - Annotated Bibliography, n.d.
  - Ethnographic Survey Schedule (Box 4)
    - "Appendix B: Ethnographic Survey Schedule", n.d.
    - Dr. Kurtz's Questionaire, 1968
    - 1974 Census by Enumeration Areas, 1974
    - List of Clans by District, 1969
  - Samori Materials (Box 4)
    - Journal of David Whitehurts (retyped: 1993 ), 1934-1835
    - "L'ascension de Samori (1861-1875)"
  - Assorted Maps (Box 4, Folder 6-8)